<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The perplex'd prince</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58725</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834709</idno>
  <idno type="VID">39213</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240908579</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223993</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834709</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99834709e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1819:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The perplex'd prince</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 130 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Allen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1682?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:1"/>
            <p>The Perplex'd PRINCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinted for <hi>R. Allen</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:4"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable WILLIAM Lord <hi>Russel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAy it Please your Lordship, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent times being Pestered with nothing but Invective Pamphlets and Scurilous Libels, most of which are cunningly design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either to invalidate the Truth of a real Plot, or to
<pb facs="tcp:39213:5"/>insinuate and prove a fict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious one, and the Bookselle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Shelves, especially their cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, being filled with no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing else but <hi>Intelligencies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Addresses, Absolom</hi> and <hi>Achit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels, Medals, Prologues, Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues,</hi> with innumerabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more of the like Tendency <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it's not easy for a <hi>Perplex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prince</hi> to get room in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Shops, or find Leasure i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Customers to perus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unpleasing Stories. <hi>The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext Prince!</hi> say some; <hi>Away with him, and tell us of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Prince, who having sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted all Difficulties, Tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples upon all that oppose him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and like the Rising Sun, marche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:39213:5"/>in Splendor and Triumph towards the Meridian of his Glory. The Perplext Prince,</hi> says others, <hi>how can that be? since he was indewed by Heaven with a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to remove all Persons that occasioned any displeasing or Perplexing Thoughts, and altho he might in the Exercise of this Power have been guilty of some kind of Injustice, yet the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Office would have wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away the stain, for Kings can do no wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, this and its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so usual to dedicate Books of this Nature to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of your Illustrious Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, that we seldom find
<pb facs="tcp:39213:6"/>any venture into the World without it, since Books have their Fates attend them, as well as Citie and Kingdoms, is the only Motive which hath imboldened me to make this attempt upon your Lordships <hi>goodness.</hi> Its proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you may think it strange that a <hi>Person</hi> with whom you are altogether unacquainted, and never saw in your life, should presume to obtrude a Dedication upon you; to which I shall only say, that although it be somewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usual, yet it is not altogether impracticable, I having seen others tread the same Path before me, whereby I was
<pb facs="tcp:39213:6"/>the more incouraged to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture after them.</p>
            <p>And so hoping this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell will afford your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship some agreeable Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion when your vacant hours from more weighty Affairs shall permit your perusal thereof, I account my self happy in having this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to subscribe my self,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordships, Most Humble and Devoted Servant,</hi> T. <hi>S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe Mind of Man doth as naturally desire Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as the Appetite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires meat, the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Food of the Soul as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is of the Body: And the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of both being agreeable to the Principles from whence they proceed, their tendency to their several Objects are as eager as the Faculties which produces them are Active. Now in the acquiring of Knowledge nothing can be more helpful than Reading, and among other sorts of Books wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the diligent Reader greedily search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and inquires after Knowledg, <hi>Novels,</hi> Romances, and allegorical Writings are not the least useful, some of which are Ancient Histories, by the diligence of Authors put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to more quaint and fluent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions
<pb facs="tcp:39213:8"/>to please the curious Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of those who are infinitely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with variety and Change. Some are dextrously designed to set forth and demonstrate the Strength and Vigour of the Passions, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally these four, <hi>viz.</hi> Love, Hatred, Jealousy and Revenge. Others are curiously designed to point out the nature of Vertue and Vice with the Benefits of the one and the Mischiefs of the other. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of others are to acquaint us with the Variety of Changes that attend the Life of man between the womb and the Coffin, the Cradle and the Grave, and the different Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wherein one and the self same man may be at different times and Seasons of his Life. The subtil Artifices, Machiavillian, Wiles, and Misterious Intreagues, which proud Ambitious and Designing men make use of, to deceive undermine and ruine all those who stand in their
<pb facs="tcp:39213:8"/>way, upon whose ruines they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to erect the Trophys of their ill gotten Victories. Together with the Vanity of all Transitory Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, since to be Royally born and descended, and Issuing from the loyns of Kings, nor yet the having been the Darlings of Mars, and the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of their Countrey, and being bless'd with a Series of Success in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bold Ʋndertaking, and heroiack Attempt, making the North and South with equal consent loudly proclaim the greatness of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Vallor, has been able to continue them in the love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of those for whom they have adventured their lives, nor some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the good opinion of their nearest Relations; nor yet to defend them from the dire Effects of the malicious whispering and mische<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious insinuations of their deadly and implacable Enemies.</p>
            <p>Such kind of writings are Genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine
<pb facs="tcp:39213:9"/>and Familiar to Persons of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Age and Quality, Sex, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion and Employment, and being so agreeable to the Inclination and Suitable to the humours of most men, they indifferently afford Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to the Young and Content to the Aged, and liberally furnishes them both with experience at other mens cost, the Stories contained in many of them are so delightful in the perusing, and Profitable in the Retaining, that they refresh the Weary, ease Troubled and Discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed Minds, and Comfort and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilerate disconsolate and Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Persons; They Solace the Tedious Hours, and beguile the slow Minutes of Pensive and tiresome watchings, and Charm anxious and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting Thoughts into a Sweet and Sedate Repose.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39213:9"/>
            <head>THE Perplexed Prince.</head>
            <p>IN <hi>Otenia</hi> there lately reigned a mighty Prince, who for many years swayed the Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter so exactly, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced Justice so imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that he seemed not to have one Enemy in all his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; but all men sate easie under his Government, and with a sweet complaisance yielded a ready com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance to all his Commands, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it as well their Happiness as their Duty to obey their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign. The King also was so vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in maintaining his Subjects Properties, that he seemed to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect his own Prerogative. In a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39213:10"/>word, there was a perfect resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of King <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Reign, wherein Peace and Plenty made the Land full of Joy; Silver was as plentiful as dust, and Gold as stones in the street; Trading flourished at home, and Merchandize abroad; Poverty and Want, Grief and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and all other displeasing things, seemed to be banished out of all his Dominions: so that you would have thought it impossible for the most malignant Spirits ever to beget any Misunderstanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Prince and People.</p>
            <p>Yet Fortune, who is always sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle and treacherous, became so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse to this happy King and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Kingdom, that on a sudden all things were changed, and so strangely altered, that those who had been absent two or three years could hardly perswade themselves that it was the same Country they so lately left possest of so much Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity: Instead of Peace, they found
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39213:10"/>War; instead of Plenty, Want; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of Riches, Poverty; all places filled with Souldiers, and nothing to be heard but the beating of Drums and the sounding of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets; instead of the sweet Charms of <hi>Venus,</hi> the loud Thundrings of <hi>Mars.</hi> The truth is, so surprizing was this Revolution, that it can be parallel'd to nothing but the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>Sodom.</hi> And as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it was strange, so was the effect of it dreadful: for this King was vanquished and deposed by his Subjects, his Queen and Children banished, and a Tyrant usurped the Kingly-power.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>West-tenia,</hi> eldest Son to this King, fled first into <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesia,</hi> then into <hi>Bogland,</hi> where he was first saluted King by the <hi>Calve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> a People that inhabited the large Province of <hi>Cross-land,</hi> being the North-part of <hi>Otenia;</hi> by whom he was invited to come to them, and take possession of that part of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39213:11"/>Kingdom, promising to be faithful and obedient Subjects, and to assist him in the recovering the rest of his Kingdom, and the placing him upon the Throne of his Ancestors. You may well suppose an Invitation of this nature, to a Prince under his circumstances, was very acceptable, and therefore readily embraced: And according to their Invitation, the first fair Wind, he wafted himself over into <hi>Cross-land.</hi> In his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage he hardly escaped being taken by the <hi>Otenians,</hi> who lay with some Ships to catch him: But being safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrived in <hi>Cross-land,</hi> he was met and welcomed by the chief Nobility and Officers of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; by whom he was with much respect and honour conducted to <hi>Burdus,</hi> where he was received and welcomed by the whole Body of the Nobility and Gentry, and a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous company of the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, and with great acclamations of Joy declared their lawful King
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39213:11"/>and Governour. Great prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were made for his Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was in a little time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in a splendid and pompous manner; and with great expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion an Army was raised to defend this, and to recover the rest of his Kingdom; over which Army the King himself is made Generalissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Otenians</hi> having intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of all that passed in <hi>Cross-land,</hi> sent a well composed Army under the command of <hi>Vall insia</hi> their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to invade them; and <hi>Vallinsia</hi> prosecuted the War with so much vigour and success, that in several Conflicts he routed the Royal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and reduced a great part of the Country to the obedience of the <hi>Otenians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King considering that the valour of the <hi>Cross-landers</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so great at home as it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and finding withal that he had a fair opportunity to invade
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39213:12"/>
               <hi>Otenia,</hi> he presently commanded his Army to advance towards it: and with great expedition he marched into <hi>Otenia,</hi> hoping to recover that Province, and reduce it to his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; which he thought more easie to do than he found it: and that which made him to apprehend it so easie, was, <hi>first,</hi> His having left <hi>Vallinsia</hi> behind him. <hi>Secondly,</hi> His surprizing them at a time when they were not prepared to receive him. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He expected that the <hi>Otenians</hi> were by this time grown weary of their new Masters, and therefore would upon his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival revolt from them to their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King. But <hi>Vallinsia</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the Kings advance into <hi>Otenia,</hi> with all imaginable speed follows him in the rear, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by prevented the Revolt of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenians;</hi> which was the Kings grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test hope.</p>
            <p>However, the King marched with his Armie through the heart
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39213:12"/>of the Countrie, and as he marcht summoned several Garisons; but none of them yielding, he march'd forward till he came to the Citie of <hi>Carranthe,</hi> where he made a halt, and march'd his Armie into the Citie; and relying upon the Justice of his Cause, and the Valour of his Souldiers, he resolved to try a pitcht Battle with <hi>Vallinsia;</hi> who follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him very close at the heels, and begirt <hi>Carranthe</hi> with his victorious Armie almost as soon as the King got into it. Accordingly the King draws out his Armie into the Field in gallant order; <hi>Vallinsia</hi> also draws up his Armie in Battalia; and both sides charg'd each other with incredible fierceness; and Victory for a considerable time was very doubtful; sometimes inclining to one side, and sometimes to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; till towards night, the King, accustomed to Misfortunes, was utterly overthrown, his Armie lost, the Royal Standard taken by his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39213:13"/>Enemies, and himself hardly esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</p>
            <p>And being by this Overthrow utterly incapacitated to attempt the recovery of his Right by force of Arms, he retired himself and some few of his Attendants into <hi>Denesia,</hi> where he was kindly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and splendidly entertained.</p>
            <p>And now we must turn our dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course from <hi>Mars</hi> to <hi>Venus,</hi> from the Stratagems of War, to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of Love: for while this Prince continued in this Court, he was frequently entertained with Balls and such-like Recreations; at one of which there was a young <hi>Cross-land</hi> Lady that waited upon the Queen of <hi>Denesia</hi> as one of her Maids of Honour, danced with such an incomparable grace, that the whole Court became her Admirers; but more especially our young King, who became instantly so in love with her, that he could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his Eyes from beholding her,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39213:13"/>but could have wish'd that the Ball might have lasted much longer; and was exceedingly grieved when it was done, and he could feast his Eyes no longer upon so delightful an Object: but while it lasted he lost not one minute, nor suffered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Object to divert him, but endeavoured to make the glances of his Eyes the Messengers of his mind, and convey the intimations of his love into the bosom of this fair one, whose surprizing Beautie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>age, had made as compleat a conquest of his Heart, as others had done of his Arms. The success was according to his wish: for the Lady whensoever she tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that way, observed the King was still looking towards her, and withal darted such amorous Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from his sparkling Eyes, that plainly demonstrated <hi>Cupid</hi> had made such a Wound in his Royal heart that would prove incurable, unless she became his Physician;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39213:14"/>which made her resolve to take a more exact view of him; and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be a handsome person, well made, very gentile, and of a Princely port and carriage, she found her self instantly surprized and taken Prisoner by those Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers he sent for that purpose from his flaming Eyes, which spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled like Diamonds in a dark night.</p>
            <p>And now they became equally concerned; he, to contrive how to meet with this fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ne, to make a declaration of his love; and she, to contrive how to give him an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of so doing. When the Ball was done, he could not excuse himself from going out with those Nobles that attended him; yet as soon as possible, he disengaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self from them, and returned in great hast to the house where the Ball was, hoping to meet with her as she came out at the door; but when he came there, he found that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39213:14"/>all the Gentry were gone: which struck him with a surprize not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that of the man who dreamt he was at a Royal Banquet whereat were all manner of Varieites; but just as he was going to fall on, he awaked, and found himself very hungry, but none of those Delicates to satisfie his craving appetite. He sometimes fancied that she had not observed him, and sometimes he fancied she had observed him, but disdainfully slighted &amp; scorned him: but presently a more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant surmize casheered all those, and he fancied she still remained within, expecting his return; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he re-entered the house, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to look for something he pretended he had lost; but when he found himself mistaken, and that she was not there, he was almost struck dead with grief. But not knowing whither to go to inform himself about the name or quality of this Lady, he returned very much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39213:15"/>discontented and mel ancholy to his Lodging; and at Supper, although he endeavoured to hide the disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his mind, by carrying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with the same pleasantness that he was wont to do, yet it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by some, who much admired what might be the occasion of it, since they had always found this Prince of such a sedate and even temper, that had with an heroick fortitude born the greatest Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
            <p>The King slept not one wink that night, but spent it wholly in thinking upon his unknown Lady: Sometimes he would revolve in his mind with much delight her incomparable Beautie, the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of her Complexion, the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness of her Features, the pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing quickness of her Eyes, and how her Smiles imbellished all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond expressions Sometimes he would contemplate his own Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, if he should obtain this fair
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39213:15"/>Creature: And sometimes he would think with grief on his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy losing so fair an opportunitie to declare his Love, and inform himself where to find the Object of it. Sometimes he would think with incredible perplexitie, that it might be a long time before he found her out; nay, that it was probable he might never be so hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie as to see her again. In what perplexitie he spent that night, I leave those to judge who have themselves had some experience in affairs of that kind.</p>
            <p>Neither was the Ladie more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie than he: for having as soon as possible taken leave of her Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, she stayed at the door on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that he might find her there; but when she had stayed till all the people were gone out, and none of her supposed Lover to appear, she departed over-whelmed with grief and melancholy, either fearing that his supposed Passion was but feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39213:16"/>or if not, that she should not be so fortunate as to find him.</p>
            <p>The rising Sun was extreamly welcome to them both, and that day they were equally busied to find out each other: he visited most of the Ladies he had any acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with, in hope to find her in some of their companies: She did the like to all those of her acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and with one of those La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies she sound several Gentlemen, one of which she remembred sate next to the King at the Ball; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon she presently begun to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of the Ball, and of the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantrie and splendour of it, especially of some strangers that were there: <hi>And pray, Sir,</hi> (said she to this Gentleman) <hi>what Illustrious Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was it that sate at your right hand? Madam</hi> (replied he) <hi>that was</hi> Conradus <hi>King of</hi> Otenia. This gave her great satisfaction, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was very much allayed with despairing apprehensions that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39213:16"/>the meanness of her Birth might be some allay to the Princes love.</p>
            <p>As for the King, he was not so fortunate, but spent several days in vain and to no purpose; so that he began to despair of finding her: But going one day to the Queens Apartment to give her a Visit, he found his fair one waiting upon the Queen. You may well imagine they were infinitely surprized to see each other so unexpectedly: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they had no opportunitie at that time to have any Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion together.</p>
            <p>Now the King was impatient to know the Name and Qualitie of this Lady whom he so much ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and therefore went in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening to visit a Lady he saw with the Queen: Where, after some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther discourse, he inquired what Lady that was that waited on the Queen to day; describing her as well as he could, by her person and dress. <hi>Pardon me, Sir,</hi> replied the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39213:17"/>Lady, <hi>I cannot apprehend which of the Ladies you mean. Methinks that is strange, Madam,</hi> replied the King, <hi>since I am very certain there was no other person there that doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way answer the description I have given your Ladyship of her. Now I call to mind who 'tis your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness means,</hi> replied the Lady; <hi>'tis one of your own Subjects, a young Lady born in</hi> Cross-land; <hi>her name is</hi> Lucilious: <hi>she is a Lady of no extraordinary Birth; but what she wants in that, is more than made up in her Beauty, Parts, and Vertues: for she is accounted one of the most accomplished Ladies in the whole Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before we proceed, we shall give the Reader the Character of this pair of Lovers. <hi>Conradus</hi> King of <hi>Otenia,</hi> was tall, finely shaped; he was of a Princely port and carriage, and had the Soul as well as the Port of a Prince, being inferiour to none in Courage and Valour.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39213:17"/>
            <p> Madam <hi>Lucilious</hi> was curiously shaped, had a round Vizage, a fair Complexion, agreeable Features, a pleasant Countenance, and a grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Bashfulness, which imbelished and gave an admirable lustre to her Beautie, and every part of her was decked with some peculiar Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; her Mind was richly fraught with the rarest qualities; she had a good Wit, a quick Apprehension; her Conversation was very modest and serious, and yet pleasant and delightful; she spake but seldom, but when she did, her words were always weightie and to the purpose, and withal so sweet and delectable, that with a pleasing kind of Magick they inchanted every Ear that heard them.</p>
            <p>The King having thus informed himself of the Name and Qualitie of his Mistriss, was not so pleased therewith as he flattered himself in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a belief that he should: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides its being contrarie to his own
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39213:18"/>inclination, he considered it was not the custom of the Kings of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenia</hi> to marry a Subject. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he resolved to give over the pursuit of his Love; which he thought was not very difficult to do, it being gone no further: To which purpose he endeavoured to banish her out of his thoughts; which he did in a great measure for two or three days.</p>
            <p>But the fourth day, as soon as he was up, he went to take the Air in the Privie-Garden; where he had not walked long, before he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spied Madam <hi>Lucilious</hi> and some other Ladies walking in the other side of the Garden; which sight begat a desire in the King of view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beautiful <hi>Lucilious</hi> once more: To which end he walked softly towards that side of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and just as he came to them, <hi>Lucilious</hi> was stooping to pluck a curious Carnation; which the King observing, stood still: and <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:39213:18"/>turning to shew the Ladies the Flower she had gathered, she was much surprized to find the King so near her, and could not forbear blushing; which gave such a lustre to her Beautie, that the King thought her far handsomer than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and as she appeared hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somer, so his love became stronger than ever. He endeavoured to check it; but all to no purpose: for now he found it irresistible. Wherefore as he walked, he burst forth into such Expressions as these: Bless me, said he, was I made for nothing but to be conquered, and born to be subdued!</p>
            <p>After this he could do nothing but think of her; and whatever he was doing, whether walking or feasting, or visiting, the Idea of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious</hi> was still in his thoughts; nay, his very sleep was not free: for no sooner were his Eyes shut, but he would be dreaming of her.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:39213:19"/>
            <p> In this perplexity he made his Brother the Prince of <hi>Pardina</hi> the Confident of his Love: for the Prince observing his Brother to be very melancholy and pensive, went early one morning to his Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and spake to the King after this manner: <hi>Dear Brother,</hi> said he, <hi>I wonder at your unkindness! Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind!</hi> said the King, interrupting him, <hi>I have never been unkind to you in my life. Nay,</hi> answered he, <hi>but you have; and I take it very ill that you have something goes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to your desires, and yet, as if I were an Enemy, or at least a stranger to you, it is kept secret from me. Truly,</hi> replied the King, <hi>I have not acquainted any one with it; but you and I are now alone, I will acquaint you with the whole business. And pray tell me,</hi> continued he, <hi>do you know Madam</hi> Lucilious? <hi>I do,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Prince, <hi>she is one of your Subjects, and a most accomplished and deserving Lady. Why that is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39213:19"/>the Lady that I have been so much concerned about; but I consider, the meanness of her Birth, and her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Subject, may disgust and offend my Friends in</hi> Otenia, <hi>and render them the less careful for my restoration. Now, Brother, pray give me your advice what is best to be done in this case, Whether to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute my designe of marrying her, or endeavour by degrees to conquer my Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince being naturally of an ambitious and aspiring mind, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately entertained some thoughts of obtaining the Crown, in case he should out-live his Brother, or of leaving it to his Children if he should die before him; and to that purpose advised the King to marry <hi>Lucilious:</hi> but to avoid disgusting the <hi>Otenians,</hi> he advised him to marry her with all the privacie ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; <hi>And have no witness of your Marriage,</hi> said he, <hi>but my self and the Priest that marries you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:39213:20"/>
            <p> The King not imagining his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had such slie and traiterous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes in this advice, highly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of it, and resolved to follow it.</p>
            <p>As soon as he was dressed, he took leave of his Brother, and went to take the Air in the Garden; where as he walked, he studied what way was best to make known his love to <hi>Lucilious;</hi> and as he thought some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on this way, and sometimes on that, he espied a Lady walking in the further side of the Garden, and walking towards her, he discovered it to be his <hi>Lucilious,</hi> who was so grieved at the seeming indifference of her Lover, that she could not sleep all night; which occasioned her being here so early.</p>
            <p>The King being not a little sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized at this unexpected happiness, retired into one of the Arbours to compose his thoughts, and resolve what to do; where he had not sate long, but Madam <hi>Lucilious</hi> having
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39213:20"/>walked her self weary, thought it convenient to retire into one of the Arbours also; and as Fortune would have it, she happened into the same Arbour where the King was, and sate down not far from him; but so were her thoughts ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up, that she saw not the King: but after she had sate some small time, happening to cast her Eyes that way, she saw him; which sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den surprize constrained her to blush; and presently rising up, she offered to go out of the Arbour; which the King (who had all this while viewed her with infinite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and pleasure) observing, rose up and accosted her after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>Madam,</hi> said he, <hi>I am infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieved at my own unhappiness, that I should be an occasion of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gusting you, and make you quit this Bower much sooner than otherwise I am confident you would have done.</hi> And with all the Rhetorick that Love and Passion could invent, he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39213:21"/>humbly entreated and pressed her continuance in the Arbour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I much wonder,</hi> replied she, <hi>your Highness should suspect your self the occasion of my going out of the Arbour, since you may be well assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I would then have left it so soon as I first entered and saw you there. Nay, Madam,</hi> replied he, <hi>I beg your pardon for that, since I am confident you did not see me, or know of my being here, till that very minute when you offered to go out; and therefore it can be nothing but my presence that could occasion your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture.</hi> And then he pressed her with a thousand perswasive Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to continue in the Arbour, offering rather to go himself, and leave her alone, than that she should depart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> replied she, <hi>you have so far prevailed, that I consent to stay, and do assure you that your person and presence is not offensive to me: I desire you would bear me company.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39213:21"/>With a very good will, Madam,</hi> replied he.</p>
            <p>When being seated, the King took her by the hand, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the purest Snow for whiteness, and kist it a thousand times: <hi>Madam,</hi> said he, <hi>when I first saw you, the Charms of your Beauty were too powerful to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted; and my yielding Heart, unable to withstand, was conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taken Prisoner at the first Charge. And pray, Madam,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, <hi>be not so cruel as to render me miserable by withstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your own happiness: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, Madam, consider the honour as well as pleasure of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conquered a King, and made your self the sole Mistriss of his Affection, and the soveraign Lady and Queen of so great a Kingdom as</hi> Otenia. <hi>You may object, I am onely a King in Title, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can expect at best but the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39213:22"/>Title of a Queen; but I shall short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be restored to my Crown and Kingdom, and then you will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Possessions and Honours, as well as the Title of a Queen.</hi> Having said these and a thousand other kind things, he ceased, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting her Answer.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>Lucilious</hi> having pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a little, replied, <hi>Sir, I must acknowledge I am unworthy of and unfit for so great an Honour as your Highness is pleased to offer me: I do acknowledge also, that when I first saw you, I did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you were in love, and found my Heart inclined to answer your flames; but then I was ignorant of your Name and Quality; which so soon as I was informed of, I cashiered (although with great difficulty) all thoughts of loving you, accounting it too great a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption for a Subject to love her Soveraign, or aspire to be a Queen.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39213:22"/>And besides, consider, I pray, that if you should marry me, it would disgust your Friends in</hi> Otenia, <hi>and make them the less desirous of your Restoration: Nay, it will also be injurious to you at present; for while you remain unmarried, several great Princes and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates may be willing to and assist you in the recovering your Right, in hope you will match with their Daughters; which they will not be so willing to do, when they shall understand you are married. Therefore although before I knew you to be my Soveraign, I lov'd you so well, that I should have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted my self the happiest of all women, if I could have obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you for my Husband; yet now I must entreat your Highness to place your Affections upon some other, who may deserve them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and whose Birth and Fortune are more suitable to yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:39213:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> replied the King with a languishing voice, <hi>if it were possible for me to make you sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how much you torment me, I flatter my self into a belief that so sweet a face cannot have so hard a heart as to persist in being cruel to one who loves you so well, and tenders your happiness more than his life. As for your Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, they are weak and frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; but if there were any weight in them, we may prevent all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies by keeping our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage secret, until we are in pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of our Crown and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although <hi>Lucilious,</hi> when she came first into the Garden, would have given a whole World, if she had had it, to have been but half so well assured of the Kings love; yet now finding it so fixt, she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to seem cruel; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore she answered him with a see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39213:23"/>indifferency, and told him, It was time for her to withdraw, and therefore she must leave him; and wishing him all imaginable happiness, she intreated him to think of some Lady that might be a more suitable Match for so great a Prince. Then rising up, and offering to depart, the King importuned her to stay longer: To which she replied, That if she were willing, yet it was not in her power to grant it, without injuring her self. Then the King offered to wait on her to her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment: To which she would by no means consent, begging his Pardon for her Refusal. But to his next Request of attending her to the Garden gate, she willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consented; where the two Lovers parted, the one visibly, but both really grieved that their Happiness lasted no longer, and wishing for a speedy and frequent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39213:24"/>renewing of such interviews.</p>
            <p>The King remained still in the Garden, on purpose to give some vent to his Passion, and ease the troubles of his mind by the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of his Complaints: <hi>Bless me,</hi> said he, <hi>was ever man so unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and miserable as I! How unsuccessful and perplext are all my Ʋndertakings! What, not able to conquer my heart, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim it from loving a Subject; nor yet to conquer her Affections, and prevail with her to love me again! Strange Fate! shall I never be fortunate and successful in any thing!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After he had taken two or three turns in the Garden, he went to his Brothers Apartment; but not finding him, he went to the Lady <hi>Arabela</hi>'s, where he found his Brother, who was as much in love with Madam <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bela,</hi> as the King was with <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious:</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:39213:24"/>To whom he related all things that had passed between him and <hi>Lucilious</hi> in the Garden; and withal told him, That the wittiness of her Answers, and her refusal of his Offers, had added new fervour to his Love. <hi>Well,</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>and you need not fear, notwithstanding her ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinacy, but that your Constancy and your Assiduities will gain her to be as kind as you would wish. I wish it may prove so,</hi> replied the King; <hi>you see I have made you the Confident of my Love, but I perswade my self you deal not so fairly with me, and that I have more reason to complain of your unkindness, than you had of mine. Pray tell me,</hi> continued he, <hi>are you not in love with Madam</hi> Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bela? <hi>I am so,</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>and have had as little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement hitherto, as you have had from</hi> Lucilious.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:39213:25"/>
            <p> After they had spent most part of the morning in such discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses as these, they parted. The King being to dine that day with the Prince of <hi>Marthano,</hi> much of their discourse at Dinner was of the Court Ladies; and amongst the rest, <hi>Lucilious</hi> came in for a share, every one highly extolling her; some, as an exquisite Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; others, for the sharpness of her Wit; some, the evenness and exactness of her Temper; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the seriousness and modesty of her Conversation. Thus all things conspired to adde new Flames to the Kings Love.</p>
            <p>From hence he went to his own Apartment; and having writ a Letter to <hi>Lucilious,</hi> he sent it by his Page; the Contents whereof, were as follow.</p>
            <p>I <hi>Am infinitely grieved, Madam, that all Declarations of Love
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39213:25"/>are alike, and that, although I am well assured I love you more than most men are used to love, yet I can find no means to express it by, but what is indifferently used by all men. However, be pleased to make reflection upon what you have observed in my Conduct to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, and I do not question but you will there find Arguments powerful enough to convince you of the reality of my Passion; and assure your self, if I love you so much, not being beloved by you, I shall much more adore you when you shall have compleated my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucilious</hi> having read this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, kist it over and over, and presently returned this following Answer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEfore I received this Letter, I thought your Highness had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39213:26"/>been in love, and that the Passion you pretend for me, was not feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but real; but I must tell you plainly, your Letter hath altered my mind, since you write like a witty man who is not really in love, but would fain perswade me to believe you so: And for that reason, together with what I told you in the Garden, I tell you as my final Answer, I can make you no such returns as you seem to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reading this Letter fill'd the King with Grief and Despair; yet the more he was repulsed, the more his Love increased, and he yet conceived some hopes, that notwithstanding those severities, <hi>Lucilious</hi> was not so cruel as she would seem. Yet Grief and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair prevailed so much, that it impaired his Health, and confined him to his Chamber three or four
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39213:26"/>days: Of which illness, and the real cause of it, he fail'd not to inform Madam <hi>Lucilious,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him but a slight Answer; yet in the close of her Letter she promised to see him the next day: which Promise effected more towards his recovery, than all the Cordials his Physicians prescribed him. Every time he waked in the night, he wished it were day; and the morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, he made shift to get up and sit by the Fire: where he had not sate long, before <hi>Lucili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> came to see him.</p>
            <p>After some Complements had passed between them, she told the King, she had been very much concerned for his indisposition, but was over-joyed to find him in so fair a way of recovery. <hi>The Promise you made me the last night,</hi> replied the King, <hi>of seeing me to day, was the onely Cordial
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39213:27"/>that hath thus far advanced my recovery; and if you would give me some hopes of making me hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, I do not question but in a day or two I shall be able to walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. Methinks,</hi> replied she, <hi>it should be beneath a Heroe, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally one that is both a King and a Souldier, to despair. Madam,</hi> replied the King, <hi>I always thought so my self, neither were all my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Misfortunes hitherto able to change my mind; but now I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Love is able to accomplish that which I always imagined could not be done. Well,</hi> said <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious, let me entreat your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to make much of your self, and entertain no thoughts that may impede or prolong your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery: for there can be nothing in the World more dear to me than your Health.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After they had spent some hours in such-like discourses as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39213:27"/>these, <hi>Lucilious</hi> departed, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending her Royal Lover to the protection of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucilious</hi> being gone, the King reflected upon, and narrowly scanned every word, interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting most of them to his own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; which so abated his Distemper, and advanced his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, that it was matter of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration both to his Physicians and the whole Court. And the second day after, he adventured abroad in his Coach to take the Air; and after Dinner he went to Madam <hi>Lucilious</hi>'s Apartment to pay his Respects to that fair one; who receiv'd him with all imaginable respect, and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with more affibility and freeness than she had hitherto done, yet with such an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, that it appeared the effect of Loyalty rather than Love. However, her Conversation was
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39213:28"/>so innocent and pleasant, that the King was infinitely pleased and delighted therewith: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they spent most part of the afternoon in this Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet they thought they had been but a moment together.</p>
            <p>But although the King was wonderfully pleased with this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, yet it grieved him to the heart that he could not certainly inform himself whether his Mistriss intended to make him happy; yet he flattered himself into a belief that she would, and took up a resolution not to rest until he knew his doom. To which purpose he visited her of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and with all the Rhetorick that Love and Passion could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, he implored her Pity, and pressed that she would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long his Misery, by refusing to grant him some Marks of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:39213:28"/>
            <p> Madam <hi>Lucilious</hi> received all his Addresses, and answered all his Importunities with so much discretion, that neither gave him cause to hope nor despair: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thought it might facilitate his designe, if he could win <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia, Lucilious</hi>'s Woman, to inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest her self in this Affair; which he found not very difficult to do: for besides her having a great Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and Respect for the King, Golden Offers, you know, are powerful Arguments, especially when joyned with large Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of future Gratuities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Percelia</hi> promised to serve him faithfully, and further his designes to the uttermost of her power. To which end she frequently spake of the King to Madam <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious,</hi> highly commending the Beauty and make of his Person, the sweetness of his Temper, with a thousand such-like things.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39213:29"/>Which that fair one was very well pleased to hear, yet it seems she did not according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom of most Ladies, make her Woman her Consident; but on the contrary, was so reserved, that <hi>Percelia,</hi> notwithstanding all her endeavours, was not able to discover how her Lady stood af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected towards the King.</p>
            <p>Which when he understood, he almost despaired of finding out the Intentions of his Mistriss: But meeting with his Brother, he acquainted him how Affairs stood between him and his Lady, and particularly of the Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he had taken up, and how he was baffled therein. To which the Prince replied, <hi>I will tell you how you shall find out whether your Mistriss be in love, or not. I,</hi> replied the King, <hi>that would do well indeed! But yet methinks. I dread knowing the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39213:29"/>truth, for fear it should be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my desires. Never fear it,</hi> replied the Prince; <hi>for I am well assured she is as much in love as you: onely Modesty, and a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular delight the fair Sex take in seeming cruel, and keeping their Lovers in a doubting condition, between Hope and Despair, when they find they have got the Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant over them, is the very reason why she conceals her Affections: Therefore my Advice is, That you go frequently to visit some Lady of her Acquaintance, and one whose Apartment is near hers, that so it may the sooner come to her know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; whereby either your self or</hi> Percelia, <hi>will without doubt discover how she stands affected: for Jealousie is a Passion more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicult to be concealed than Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Accordingly, the very next day he visited Madam <hi>Salmuna,</hi> who was accounted one of the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somest
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39213:30"/>Women about the Court, and one who was frequently visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Lucilious.</hi> The King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his Visits every day for a considerable time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Percelia</hi> was the first that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her Lady with this News; and according to her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions from the King, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to perswade her that the King was in love with Madam <hi>Salmunia,</hi> and intended to marry her. But Madam <hi>Lucilious,</hi> who had abundance of Wit, presently fathomed the very depth of the designe; and being well assured of the Kings Love, she was not at all concerned about it.</p>
            <p>So that the King found this Expedient would not do; which forced him to wrack his Invention to find out another: which was, to cause a Report to be spread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that he would leave <hi>Dene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia,</hi> and travel into <hi>Andruno.</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:39213:30"/>This Stratagem took according to his wish: for his Brother going to visit a Lady of <hi>Lucilious</hi>'s ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, found Madam <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious</hi> with her. This Lady, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other things, enquired how the King did. <hi>Madam,</hi> said he, <hi>my Brother is very well in health, but we are like to lose him, for he intends within these two days to set forward towards</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druno. <hi>I hope you are not in earnest,</hi> said the Lady. <hi>It's very true, Madam,</hi> replied the Prince, who all this while observed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Lucilious,</hi> to see if she dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd any kind of concernedness about it. And although she said nothing, yet he observed her Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to come and go, as if the News were not onely unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but very unwelcome to her.</p>
            <p>The Prince fail'd not that night to acquaint the King with what
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39213:31"/>had passed, and particularly the Concernedness he had discovered in <hi>Lucilious</hi> by her change of Countenance. The King over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed at the Relation, resolved to follow his good Fortune.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, the next morning he went into the Garden to take the Air, but chiefly in hopes to meet with his Mistriss, whom he knew took great delight to sre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent those Flowery Walks; where about half an hour after his arrival, he saw <hi>Lucilious</hi> enter. He endeavoured to prevent his being discovered by that fair one, that so he might with the more convenience observe whether she appeared melancholy or discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented: And when he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served her as long as he thought convenient, he came out of the Arbour where he had sheltered himself from her sight, just as she came at it; and after salutation,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39213:31"/>the King spake after this manner. <hi>You know, fair Creature, with what a passionate Zeal I have sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitated your Love, and how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse you have always appeared to my desires, which hath reduced me to the cruel necessity of removing from</hi> Denesia <hi>into</hi> Andruno; <hi>and I intend to morrow to begin my Journey. And, Madam,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued he, <hi>I am very glad of my meeting you so fortunately this morning, to take my leave of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adyship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never was Surprize equal to hers: for she stood like one struck dumb, and utterly bereaved of Sence; sometimes fixing her eyes upon the King, sometimes on the ground, not knowing what to do or say in this case; now resolving on this, and presently on the quite contrary. The King easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the distractions and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities of her mind, by what
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39213:32"/>he saw in her Countenance; but at last she brake silence, and said, <hi>I must acknowledge, Sir, that as nothing could have fallen out more unexpected than your departing from</hi> Denesia, <hi>since I always thought you intended to make it the place of your Residence, until Heaven should please to restore you to the Throne of your Ancestors; so nothing could have fallen out more to my grief: And I would it were in my power to divert you from this Journey, and procure your consent to continue here.</hi> She would have proceeded, but was not able, so excessive was her Grief and Amazement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> replied the King, <hi>you are the onely cause of my removal: for since you will not make me happy by complying with my Love, I am not able to continue in a place where I must dayly augment my misery, by frequent seeing the occasion of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:39213:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> said <hi>Lucilious,</hi> interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, <hi>if my unkindness be the thing you have laid so much to heart, I promise you, if you would be but so kind to put off your Journey upon my request, I will endeavour to shew you so much kindness that you shall have no cause to repent it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was within this three days,</hi> replied the King, <hi>in your power to have prevented not onely my Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, but the very thoughts of it; but now 'tis too late: for having provided and ordered all things for my Journey, I cannot alter it, although you should now promise to answer my desires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At these words <hi>Lucilious</hi> fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and had she not been suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by her Lover, had fallen to the ground; but being come to her self, with a dejected Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and a languishing Voice, she entreated him not to be so
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39213:33"/>cruel, but either retract that dreadful and killing Resolution, or else permit her to go with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> replied the King, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of those things can be; but this I will promise you, that I will return as soon as I can convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is more than I intended; but then you must resolve to make me happy at my return. Make you happy,</hi> said she, <hi>how do you mean by that? By consenting to make me your Husband,</hi> said the King. <hi>Cruel man!</hi> said she, <hi>if you persist in your Resolution, your absence will make me so miserable, that it will be out of my power to make you happy at your return.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words were spoken with such a languishing and mournful voice, the Tears in the mean while trickling down her Cheeks like so many Pearls, that the King finding his heart toucht
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39213:33"/>with Compassion, could hardly refrain comforting his dejected Lover, by acquainting her with the whole Design and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of this pretended Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but remembring how cruel she had been to him, he resolved to leave her in that uncertain and perplex'd condition, that so she might be convinced by her own experience what he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured upon her account: And therefore pretending to take his last Farewel of her, telling her, <hi>He should neither have time nor opportunity to see her again before his Departure,</hi> he retired to his Lodgings, and <hi>Lucilious</hi> to hers. <hi>Lucilious</hi> being got to her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, shut up her self in her Chamber, and gave a free vent to her Passions: But having given some ease to her afflicted mind, by the freeness of her Complaints, and by the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39213:34"/>of her Tears, she began to consider that this Journey might not be really intended, but was onely invented as a Stratagem to find out her Affections; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore she presently called <hi>Percelia,</hi> and inquired if she had heard any report that the King of <hi>Otenia</hi> was going to <hi>Andruno: No, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> replyed <hi>Percelia, I have heard no such thing. Pray go you,</hi> said <hi>Lucilious, and see if you can learn the truth of it: for I am informed he goes to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Percelia</hi> went; and having learned that there was nothing of truth in the report of the Kings Journey into <hi>Andruno,</hi> returned and acquainted her Lady. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious</hi> having asked her divers times, if she were certain she was not mis-informed, she assured her that there was no such Journey intended, or so much as talked of;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39213:34"/>which confirmed <hi>Lucilious</hi> in her opinion, that it was a Stratagem of the Kings, to find out whether she were in love with him or not. She was extreamly pleased that she was not to lose her Lover, and looked upon this as a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the reality of the Kings Passion; and now nothing grieved her, but the having dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered her own.</p>
            <p>The King not doubting but <hi>Lucilious</hi> had inquired into the truth of his pretended Journey, went in the afternoon to see her, and perceived her to be very much discomposed and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly. So soon as he entered her Chamber, she reproached him for taking that advantage of the weakness of her Sex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> replied the King, <hi>I beg your pardon for that; and I think you have reason to grant it, since you know I tried all other
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39213:35"/>ways to know your Resolution, and could not prevail: Wherefore although it would have been Death to me to know I was not belov'd by you, yet accounting one Death better then many, I resolved on this Project, and therefore you may thank your self: And since we now know one anothers minds, let us fool no more; but resolve to compleat each others Happiness by appointing the day of Marriage.</hi> To which she consenting, they were privately married, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Prince of <hi>Purdino</hi>'s Advice; and about Ten Months after she was brought to Bed of a Son; at whose Birth the King was so exceedingly pleas'd, that taking the Royal Infant into his Princely Arms, <hi>Sweet Babe,</hi> said he, <hi>thou art born Heir to a Crown, and although thy Father be at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent out of possession thereof, yet he hopes shortly to recover it, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39213:35"/>leave thee in the quiet injoyment of it; and if Heaven has decreed I shall die before I obtain the pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session thereof, yet it will be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to me, that I leave such a Branch behind me to revenge my Wrongs, and recover my Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> The King and Queen both agreed he should be called <hi>Heclacious,</hi> which was the name of his Great Grand-Father, and his Uncle the Prince of <hi>Purdino.</hi> Soon after the Queens going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, the Prince of <hi>Purdino</hi> was privatly married to Madam <hi>Arabelia,</hi> none being made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewith but the King and Queen.</p>
            <p>The King took so much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and satisfaction in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant and innocent Conversation of his Queen and her young Son, that he almost forgot his former Calamities, and lived as pleasant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with almost as much ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39213:36"/>and splendour, as if he had been in the possession of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: but his pleasure was short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived, and all his Joys were sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly overturned and lost, by the death of the Queen.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Otenians</hi> began now to long for the return of their King; they having learned to know the worth of so excellent a Prince as he was, by the want of him, they began to have an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary esteem and veneration for him; which was very much heightned by the dayly Reports they received of his just Praises from those places where he at present lived; every one who had the happiness to know him, highly commending him for a valiant; wise, and religious Prince. Great endeavours were used by his Enemies to prevent his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; but the <hi>Calvenians,</hi> a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and powerful People, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39213:36"/>the most considerable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Otenians,</hi> both for Number, Sobriety, and Wealth, took part with him; and having prepared all things for his Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they sent and humbly invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and entreated him to return to the possession of his Throne, and the excercise of his Kingly Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Which he promised to do: And to prepare all in general to be willing to receive him, he sent a General Pardon for all Crimes that had been committed against him, to all those who would lay down their Arms.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Purdino</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing his Brother was likely to recover his Kingdom, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either grown weary of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belia,</hi> or else hoping upon his Brothers restoration to marry with some great Princess, took oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, from the secrecy of their Marriage, to deny her being his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39213:37"/>Wife, disavowing all Contracts of Marriage between them.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>Arabelia</hi> being infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med hereof by her Friends, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to divert him from his Resolution, by reproaching him for his Unkindness, in his ungrateful and injurious deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her being his Wife, admiring how he could act contrary to his Conscience, and so willingly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate his Marriage Vows so so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly made and often repeated; yet all this availed her little, for the Prince still affirmed, he was not Married.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>Arabelia</hi> finding she could not perswade the Prince from his Resolution, she resolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to apply her self to the King, who was not only present at the Marriage, but she knew him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to be an unparallel'd Prince for his Justice and Equity, and therefore going to his Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39213:37"/>and falling down before him, she implored his Pity and Compassion. The King being surprized thereat, presently took her by the hand, and lifted her up, demanding what Suit she had to prefer to him, assuring her he would serve her to the uttermost of his power: <hi>Why then,</hi> said the Princess, <hi>your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness very well knows, that your Brother the Prince of</hi> Purdino <hi>did for a long time solicit my love, and would not let me be at quiet, but wearied me with his daily Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to consent to marry him; you know also that at last I consented, and we were privately married; which your Highness knows was to prevent any damage coming thereby to your Interest: Your Highness was present when we were married, and are the only Witness I have to prove my mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:39213:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> replied the King, <hi>all this I acknowledge to be true; but what hath occasioned your coming to me in this manner, I cannot apprehend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it please your Highness,</hi> said she, <hi>the Prince, like a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less ungrateful man, denies all this, and affirms he was never married to me, or had to do with me otherwise than as I was his Whore; whereby unless your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness approve your self more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and just than your Brother, I shall not onely lose my Husband, but that also which is much dearer to me than my life, my Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Honour, and be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted little better than a common Strumpet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is it possible,</hi> said the King, <hi>that my Brother should be so wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! It is too true,</hi> replied the Princess.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> said the King, <hi>satisfie
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39213:38"/>your self, and rely upon the word of a King, that I will oblige my Brother not to proceed in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution; but instead of affirming that you are not, he shall openly and publickly acknowledge and own you for his Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I humbly thank your Highness,</hi> replied the Princess, <hi>and do not in the least distrust your exact performance of the Royal Promise you made me; but do promise my self, as the consequence of it, a Happiness which will last as long as my Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King sent for the Prince the next day, and reproached him for his Treachery and Unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness towards the Princess. <hi>Sir,</hi> said the Prince, <hi>since you are now returning to the possession of your Kingdom, it would be as much for your Honour and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest as mine, that I should marry with some great Princess that may
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39213:39"/>inrich and strengthen us, by the largness of her Dowry, and the greatness and potency of her Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and since there is none knows I am married but your self, I may deny it with the more Confidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hate your baseness, <hi>replyed the King,</hi> and I must tell you that you talk not like a Prince: if you were now unmarried and so at Liberty to take your choice, it were better to marry as you say, with some great Princess; but since you have made a Choice already, I will by no means suffer her to be so grossly abused; and therefore I command you to own her publickly for your wife. Since it is your Royal pleasure, I shall not dispute your command, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the Prince,</hi> but yield a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obedience thereunto, if your Highness will please to go with me and pacify her for the wrong
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39213:39"/>I have done and intended to do her. To which the King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting, they were perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and the Prince publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared his Marriage.</p>
            <p>The King having prepared and ordered all things for his return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Otenia,</hi> he was received and entertained with all the honour and glory imaginable, and the greatest tokens of Joy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of Loyalty that ever any Prince received, and placed upon the Throne of his Kingdom, with more pomp and splendor than ever any of his Predecessors the Kings of <hi>Otenia</hi> had been. The King made his Young Son Prince of <hi>Burranto,</hi> he grew to be a very hopefull Prince, being the very Picture and Image of his Father, and delighted in nothing more than in learning Military Discipline, and exercising him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in feats of war.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:39213:40"/>
            <p> The Prince of <hi>Purdino</hi> had his thoughts now wholly taken up in contriving how he might se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Succession to himself, or his Children; to which purpose he consulted with his Wives Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a cunning politick Blade, whose opinion was, that there be a Match proposed for the King with <hi>Berrelia,</hi> Daughter to the King of <hi>Legantine,</hi> who was a beautifull Lady, but somewhat in years; so that it was probable she might have no Children. This Advice was highly approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Prince, and presently put in execution; and her Beauty praised and extolled to the Skies, and set off with so many flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes, that the King became ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly in love with her: and the onely Obstruction was the Prince of <hi>Burranto,</hi> the <hi>Legantines</hi> refusing to consent to the Match, unless they might be assured that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39213:40"/>the Issue the King should have by <hi>Berrelia</hi> should succeed him.</p>
            <p>The King was unwilling to consent to this; yet such was the excess of his Love, which was extreamly heightned by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices of the Prince and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law, who were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally commending her for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite Beauty; insinuating, that although if <hi>Lucilious</hi> had lived, the King could not in point of Conscience have denied his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, yet she being dead, and none concerned therein but a Child, the King might safely do it to serve a present turn; and if his Highness saw occasion for it, he might right the young Prince at any time. By which means the King was prevailed upon to acknowledge that the Prince of <hi>Burranto</hi> was Illegitimate, and that he was never married to his Mother. Whereupon the Match
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39213:41"/>was concluded on, and consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, to the great Joy of both Countries.</p>
            <p>The Prince finding his contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to succeed well hitherto, was the more incouraged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed therein; and knowing that the <hi>Calvenians,</hi> who had resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Brother to the Kingdom, would be the greatest obstruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of his designs; for besides their loving and having a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er veneration for the Kings Son, they were very Jealous of the Prince of <hi>Pordino,</hi> fearing least he being brought up and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his Mother, who was a <hi>Gregorian,</hi> he might be of the same Religion; he indeavoured both by himself and his Emissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to represent them to the King as a Traiterous and disloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al People, insinuating that they had taken part with the King only to serve a present turn, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39213:41"/>that having obtained their end they would be the first that should seek an opportunity to desert him, and that therefore it would be the Kings interest to desert them, and take part with the <hi>Pontificarians,</hi> who had many of them remained Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the King all the time of his Trouble.</p>
            <p>The good services of the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venians</hi> were yet so fresh in the Kings memory, that he was hardly drawn to consent to this, but wearied with their dayly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, and being somewhat inclined to believe those false Stories, which though invented by them, yet were reported with so much confidence and forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that they had the appearance of truth; it was at last resolved on and put in execution, and the <hi>Calvenians</hi> were turned out of the Kings Favour and thrust from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39213:42"/>all Places of Profit and Trust: and as if this were not enough, they procured several Laws to be made against them, as Enemies to the King and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The thing the Prince took care for next, was to get his own Creatures, and those that had their dependance on him, and therefore would be at his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, placed about the King: by which means there were very few promoted to any Places of Profit or Trust, either Civil or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, but by his direction and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence; and those few that were not, he always by false insinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions got them discarded. Most of those promoted by him were <hi>Gregorians;</hi> for which People he procured so much favour, that they were connived at, and the Laws were not so vigorously put in execution against them as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; and although they were
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39213:42"/>always false and treacherous to the King's Predecessors, even those that were of their own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yet now they must be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed the most Loyal Subjects, and the Kings best Friends.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Burranto</hi> having signalized his Valour, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himself both a wise and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious General, he grew so much in favour with his Father, that he gave him several great Offices both of Profit and Trust, and made him one of the greatest men in <hi>Otenia:</hi> Whereat his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, although he seemed to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well pleased, yet he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly grieved to the heart; but although he resolved to ruine him, he was not able to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish it at present.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Priviledges the <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> enjoyed under the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Reign of <hi>Conradus,</hi> by means
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39213:43"/>of the Prince of <hi>Purdino,</hi> they were not therewith content, but greatly desiring to have their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion the Religion established by Law, which could notbe whilst <hi>Conradus</hi> lived, they began to think he had raigned long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enough; and since he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably out-live the Prince, and thereby cut off their aspiring hopes, they entered into a cursed conspiracy and combination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his life, resolving to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy him, thereby to make way for restoring <hi>Gregorianism,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <hi>Otenia,</hi> to the obedience of the <hi>Pontify:</hi> to which purpose they gave directions to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Emissaries about the King, to rail against the <hi>Calvenians,</hi> and insinuate that they were Plotting some Treasonable practises a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Kings life, which was so dextrously performed by the Princes Creatures, that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39213:43"/>belief; from whence they expected a double advantage, that the King by being afraid of the <hi>Calvenians,</hi> who intended him no hurt, would rest secure as to them, whereby they should have the greater advantage to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him; which when they had done, they resolved to lay it upon the <hi>Calvenians,</hi> thereby to excite the people to join with them in destroying of them, which was their other advantage. And that they might make sure work, they with great sums of money procured abundance of despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate villains to undertake the, murther, some were to attempt it by poyson, some by stabbing, some by pistolling, and some by other ways. But Heaven, that is always tender of the Life of Princes, especially ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ones, caused such a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and Consternation to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39213:44"/>seiz one of the Conspirators, that he discovered the <hi>Gregorians</hi> Conspiracy to the King: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon several Nobles were appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and divers of the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains who had undertaken the Murther. The Conspiracy was so plainly proved, that the King was perfectly satisfied of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and truth thereof, and great care was taken for the Kings safety.</p>
            <p>The Prince was very much sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized at this Discovery; and the more, because one of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants was apprehended as one of the chief Conspirators; and he was afraid he would discover things that he was unwilling should be known. Great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulting there was with his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidents what should be done to prevent <hi>Coldero</hi>'s discovering, and to prevent the Kings concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any ill opinion of the Prince.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39213:44"/>As to the first, it was resolved, They must take great care to feed <hi>Coldero</hi> with hopes that the Prince would procure a Pardon for him, which should be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the place of Execution, upon condition he did not reveal any thing that he knew of the <hi>Gregorians</hi> Conspiracy. As to the second, their advice was, That the Prince must go and fall down at the Kings feet, and by great Protestations of his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, endeavour to confirm him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in the King's good opinion. Accordingly the Prince going to visit the King, fell down at his feet, and spake to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dread Soveraign, and most dear Brother, it was not without Grief and Anguish, as well as Shame and Confusion, that I received the first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nformation of a cursed Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acy and Combination against <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our sacred Life, carried on by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39213:45"/>the Gregorians and now by the goodness of the Celestial Power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and I hope defeated; and knowing that my being of the same Religion might render me obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to your Censure, and I might be suspected as Author of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy, or at least that I conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at it and concealed it, I thought my self obliged to come in this manner and make a solemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of my innocency, I call the Heavenly Powers to witness that I knew not directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly of any Treason, Conspiracy or Combination, against your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness by any Person whatsoever; and that there is no Person in</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenia <hi>that</hi> Abhors <hi>such wicked and treasonable practises more then my self, which I humbly beseech your Highness to beleive, or else take this Sword and end my days therewith, for I desire to live no longer than I may aprove my self
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39213:45"/>a Loyal and obedient Subject, and enjoy the Honour of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses Favour and good opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King having raised him up, made him this following Answer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When I consider the many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Priviledges I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed upon you, I know not how to imagine you can plot Treason against me, yet when I consider you were still buzzing in my ears that the</hi> Calvenians <hi>were forming a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy against me, which as far as I can be informed is false, it makes me suspitious that you were too well acquainted with the</hi> Gregorian <hi>Conspiracy, and designed by those reports to prevent my having any suspition thereof; whereby my ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine might be the more unavoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and that which confirms me in this opinion is</hi> Coldero<hi>'s being charged as one of the chief Managers of this Conspiracy. May
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39213:46"/>it please your Highness,</hi> replyed the Prince, <hi>I am extreamly grieved that any</hi> Gregorian <hi>should be so wicked and Treacherous, especially any that live in my Family or have any dependence upon me, and therefore I beseech you to shew them no favour, but wrack them, Hang them, quarter them, or let them be torn to pieces by wild Horses, or put to the most cruel death that can be invented; especially that Villian</hi> Coldero.</p>
            <p>The King hearing his Brother exclaim so much against the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators, was fully persuaded of his innocency.</p>
            <p>Soon after this, <hi>Coldero</hi> and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other of the Conspirators were Condemned and Executed for their Treason; <hi>Coldero</hi> went very couragiously to the place of Execution, where with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Countenance he confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently denied he knew of any
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39213:46"/>Conspiracy against the King, affirming he was falsely accused; relying upon the Princes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of procuring him a Pardon; but when he saw the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ready to do his Office, and no Pardon produced, he begun to change couler, and look Pale, yet considering it might be so ordered by the Prince that the Pardon should not be produced till the last <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>nity, and if he should confess any thing, it should not be produced at all, and so between hope and despair, he dyed affirming his innocency; the Prince and all the <hi>Gregorians</hi> being glad they were so well rid of him that might have discovered all their Villany.</p>
            <p>The Prince always when he came to see his Brother, fail'd not to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eterated and solemn Protestations of his Innocency; advising the King to take great
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:39213:47"/>care of his Person, to search to the bottom of this Conspiracy, and not to spare any that were found guilty, but as terror to all Traitors execute upon them the utmost severities of the Law, yet he gave secret Instructions to those about the King, that they should sometimes as they found opportunity be speaking in the Kings presence of the great difficulty the <hi>Gregorians</hi> would have found in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishing those Treasons, which were laid to their charge; some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time they should discourse with much admiration of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of their folly, in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating such horirble Treasons, to such base and mean Persons, a thing hardly practicable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the greatest Fools. They were ordered likewise to speak in the Kings presence, with great amazement and admiration, of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:39213:47"/>
               <hi>Colderos</hi> and the other <hi>Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> that were executed absolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and solemnly denying with their dying Breath. There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any way guilty of those Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons laid to their charge, or that they were Privy too, or knew of any Conspiracy against the King. And sometimes they were to raise discourses concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Calvenians</hi> former rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that it might paradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be a contrivance of theirs to forge a conspiracy against the <hi>Gregorians,</hi> and hire those wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses to prove it, that so they might thereby bring about some cursed Conspiracy of their own, to the ruine of the King and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>These Instructions were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly followed by the Princes Creatures about the King and the things so frequently hinted and interwoven with so many
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39213:48"/>subtil Insinuations of the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility thereof, that the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to listen, unto their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, and by insensible degrees grew into a Jealousy of the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venians,</hi> and to have better thoughts of the <hi>Gregorians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their next Contrivance was to procure a general belief among the People, either that there was really no such Conspiracy car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by the <hi>Gregorians</hi> as was proved against them, but that it was a malicious contrivance of the <hi>Calvenians,</hi> thereby to get the <hi>Gregorians,</hi> (whom they always hated) to be utterly destroyed, or at worst, that it was only a Plot to introduce the <hi>Gregorian</hi> Religion into <hi>Otenia,</hi> without having any such Bloody and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous design against the Kings Life. This was so difficult an undertaking by reason the thing was so plainly proved, and the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39213:48"/>People so generally possessed with the truth of it, that it was long before they could come to any resolution, what method to take in the effecting their desires: many meetings and consultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they had, sometimes resolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon one way, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an other; but whilst they thus spun out time without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any resolution, one of their Company stood up, and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself to the Prince, spake as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You know</hi> Great Sir, <hi>we have been long prosecuting a Design to place you on the Throne, and to root out the</hi> Lutaranian, <hi>and establish the</hi> Gregorian <hi>Religion, and when we were just upon the point of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishing our desire, and obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the happiness in the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation whereof we had so long pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and delighted our selves, we were strangely frustrated by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39213:49"/>of base vile perjured Fellows, who contrary to their solemn Oaths and Protestations, discovered all our designs. And that since al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering our measures, we still resolve in spite of Fate and Mager all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to accomplish our designs, and by making the best of a bad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, frustrate the design of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and by bringing it into a general discredit, render our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries more secure, and thereby the more easily prevailed against, we have proceeded well hitherto, having made the King to stagger in his beliefe of the Conspiracy, and there remains nothing but the work ing the People into the same tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and yet as if we had lost all our courage. We spend all our time in Consultation and give our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies opportunities to search further into our designs, and by offers of Pardon procure more of our Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, to discover our Treasons,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39213:49"/>and then it may be too late for us to undermine them, therefore let us resolve on what course to take before we part, and when we have concluded on our methods, let us banish all fear and timrousness and like men of courage and resolution let us bare up against all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whatsoever.</hi> You have spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken very well, <hi>said the Prince,</hi> but pray Sir proceed and tell what you think is to be done in this extremity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> replyed he, <hi>I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, since we have wrought upon the Kings good nature to doubt of the reality of our designs against him, you must make use of your power and interest with him and his chief Officers to prevail with them to discourage the Witness by frowning on them, and first l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sning and then taking away their Pensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which will not only prevent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from coming in, but parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39213:50"/>make them fall out amongst themselves, and contradict one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Secondly you must pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them to frown upon and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage those Magistrates that are most buisy in searching into our designs then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you must by pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing the King that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their business was designed only to get into the favour of the Robble, and excite them to Rebel get them disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and turned out of their several Offices, upon which we must cause Papers to be scattered about, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they must be accused of divers Frauds and other unjust things which they Committed under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of searching for</hi> Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. <hi>Thirdly, we must whatsoever it cost us, and what difficulty soever we meet with therein, turn the Conspiracy upon the</hi> Calvenians, <hi>to which purpose we must get some ingenious fellows whose extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance hath reduced them to such
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39213:50"/>extremities and wants that they will for a little present pay, and promise of future rewards, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take whatsoever we shall imply them in, to write and scatter Papers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, to amuse people with a noise of a Conspiracy against the King, carried on by the</hi> Calvenians, <hi>that so we may prepare people to beleive it when we shall have gotten things ready for a discovery of it. We must likewise get a great number of Letters written, which must im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port matters of Treason and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Conspiracy against the King, which Letters must by some bold and desperate Villians, who will to serve a present turn and supply their pinching necessity, undertake the most difficult and hazzardous designs, knowing that if they should be discovered, they have neither Estates nor Credit to lose, and therefore their Condition cannot well be worse then it is; but on the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39213:51"/>contrary if they succeed their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are thereby made for ever) be lodged in the houses of some of the chief</hi> Luteranians, <hi>especially those of the</hi> Calvenian <hi>way, and when they have lodged them they must repair immediately to some Officers and accuse them of Treason and desire to have their houses searched, which being done, and those Letters seized it will confirm their accusation, and there is no question but we shall get them Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and Executed as Traitors to the King and Kingdom, and by this Pollicy we shall make the King and the</hi> Luteranians <hi>do that for us which we could not accomplish our selves, and destroy their best Friends and our worst enemies, and that by their own Laws too, whereby they will prepare our way to compleat the ruine of them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Council was very well liked and highly apployed by
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39213:51"/>the Prince and the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and they resolved to follow it as the most likely way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and the Prince and all the rest in their several Station, used their endeavour to promote the blessed work which they found no great difficulty in effecting, for the King was so well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded of his brothers Fidelity, that he readily believed whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Prince advised was for his honour and security, and withall loved him so passionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he had no power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him any thing he requested, and for the Officers about the King there was no difficulty in prevailing with them, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Princes Creatures, and therefore at his devotion, they procured many others also to join with them, who looking upon the Prince as the only ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing man in <hi>Otenia,</hi> readily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39213:52"/>his interest, and some of those had been great opposers of the Prince and his designs, who to ingratiate themselves the more in his favour, promised to draw over as many of their former Associates as possible to his interest, and ruine all those who would not be allured by procuring Treason to be sworn against them.</p>
            <p>Things having thus far an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered their desires and a bold daring and adventerous Blade being procured and presented to the Prince, who would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the conveying what Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Papers they should think convenient, into the Houses of the Chief <hi>Luteranians,</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing moreover to swear any kind of Treasonable words against them which they should direct; The Prince took leave of his Brother, pretending business into
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39213:52"/>the remote parts of <hi>Otenia,</hi> hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his return to find all his designs effected. But before he went, he procured the Prince of <hi>Burranto</hi> to be banished, out of the Kings presence, and degraded of all his Offices, notwithstanding the King had not long before imbraced him with the greatest Passion imaginable, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was the greatest support and comfort he had in the world.</p>
            <p>The Prince was no sooner gone, but they began to put their designs in practice, and this bold fellow adventured to convey a bundel of Treasonable papers into the Chamber of Captain <hi>Brodrick,</hi> a very Loyal Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as were all the rest who were to have been cut off by this means; but so unfortunate was this bold Champion of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorian</hi> cause in his first attempt, which certainly was begun upon
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39213:53"/>an unlucky day, that it utterly overthrow and dashed the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign before ever it came to any Maturity, for he was taken in the fact, and the thing so plainly proved upon him, that he was committed to the Black Tower: it being the very same place to which he hoped to have had the Captain committed, this put a stop to their further proceedings and if there were any words in our Language more comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, then surprize and anguish, I would make use of them here to express the Amazement and Sorrow of the <hi>Gregorians,</hi> for the unexpected discovery of this well laid Plot, which was so cunningly contrived and manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with such machiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llion Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty that they thought it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, even for Heaven it self to frustrate it; but that which most confounded them, was the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39213:53"/>fear they were in, that <hi>Delego</hi> would in hopes to save his life discover the whole villanous and hellish Contrivance, wherefore all heads were at work to find out a way to prevent it, to which end they sent private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions to <hi>Delego,</hi> how he should behave himself and what he should say when he was Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, assuring him if he would resolutely deny all, they did not question but it would take ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, still promising withal that if it came to the worst and they could not get him cleared, yet they would not fail to procure him a Pardon, and as an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their present care and respect for him, they sent him by the same Messenger 50 pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gold, but <hi>Delego</hi> consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how they had served o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and not liking to be <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derized</hi> out of his life, revealed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39213:54"/>the Truth and thereby obtained the Kings Pardon. Which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of his, aded to their grief, and augmented their confusion, so that they knew not what to do, they presently advertized the Prince hereof, desiring his advice in this dangerous Affair, which unless wisely managed, would involve him and all his adherents into unavoydable ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</p>
            <p>The Reading these Letters filled the Prince with a Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Rage and Fury; Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and banning the Stares, and exclaiming against Fortune for having so often crossed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, vowing that if ever he got the ascendant of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, he would wreck his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon them, and although by these frequent disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the stroke be the longer before it reach them, yet it shall
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39213:54"/>fall the heavier at last, and those damn'd <hi>Luteranians</hi> shall know the fatal consequence of falling under my indignation and wrath, for I sware by the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices Godship, I will not, no I will not spare one of them, nor sheath my Sword until I have with this all-Conquering Arm utterly destroyed them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguished the very name and Memory of them in <hi>Otenia.</hi> It was a considerable time before he could Conquer his Rage so much as to permit him the ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring into a serious consideration what was best to be done in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to prevent that ruine this Discovery would necessarily bring upon him if not speedily prevented; but being a little cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, he retired into his Closet, and knowing how passionately the King loved him, as well for his being his constant Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:39213:55"/>when he was in <hi>Denesia,</hi> as the nearness of their Relation and that therefore he would not easily believe him Guilty of Conspiring Treason against him, or if he were a little jealous of him it would be no difficult task to take off those jealousies and establish himself again in his good opinion by a submisive Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter stuffed with solemn prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations of his innocency, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horences of all such Treasonable Crimes as were laid to his charge, imputing it to the malice of his enemies thereby to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish his ruine, and so to make way for the ruine of himself, wherefore between hope and despair, he writ the following Letter to the King.</p>
            <p>I may it please your Highness, <hi>Account my self the most misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and unfortunate man living, in that I have been more than once
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:39213:55"/>accused as a disloyal Traitor, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though no man was ever more car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to approve himself a Loyal and Obedient Subject; whereof I hope to find such a Testimony in your Royal Breast as may plead better in my behalf than I can plead for my self, I must confess my Enemies have laid their designs so deep and mysterious that I am not able to fathom them my self, much less expound them to you; and therefore they being so Confident and Positive in their accusation, I shall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by words and arguments to prove my Innocency; but shall leave it wholly to your wisdom and goodness, beseeching you to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on these things as contrived by the</hi> Calvenians, <hi>(who always ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested an implacable hatred to me) to work my ruine, and I wish I could say mine only, but I fear they have a further design there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and that no less then your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Life, which they can never
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39213:56"/>effect so well whilst I live, I So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly Protest and Swear by all that is Sacred, I know nothing of all those things whereof I am ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused, but do assure you that if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of those things be proved against me by any substantial Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, I will renounce all pardons, and willingly bear that Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which those crimes justly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King having read this Letter knew not what to think; never was Prince so perplext in his thoughts, not being able to resolve whether to believe the Prince, and the <hi>Gregorians</hi> had conspired his Life, or else that the <hi>Calvenians</hi> had plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to charge them with so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in hopes to get them destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet what <hi>Delego</hi> witnessed was so plain and positive, and his Evidence strengthned with so many concurring Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:39213:56"/>that the King became somewhat more Jealous of his Brother then he had been, which the Prince understanding hast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all speed to Court, not forgetting to prepare his way by two or three insinuating Letters; to sweeten the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a better opinion of him, which was very much promoted by his Creatures who were always speaking in the Kings presence of the Princes former Service and Loyalty to the Crown. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived at Court the next day, he went to pay his respects to the King, and when he came into his presence he fell down on his knees, and with his hands lifted up to Heaven, spake as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am once more accused of Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treason against your Life, who they were that contrived this against me, and set</hi> Delego <hi>on
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:39213:57"/>to charge me, with such horrid Crimes (the very thought whereof I always abhorr'd with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Detestation imaginable, for the truth whereof I appeal to the great God who searches the Heart and is perfectly acquainted with the most secret Intentions of the Mind;) I cannot yet tell, you what it is they aim at in thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring my ruine, I fear no good to your Highness, I wish you were as safe as I am Innocent, and were in no more danger from them then you are from me, for I call the Almighty to witness that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, directly or indirectly Plot any Treason against you, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised, assisted or incouraged any other Person whatsoever in so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor was I ever made acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with or concealed any Treason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able designs managed by the</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorians <hi>against your Life and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and if this which I now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:39213:57"/>be not true, I wish all the fearful Judgments that ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell a Traitor and a perjured Wretch may befal me, and I may be made an Example to all Succeeding Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King not imagining his Brother had a dispensation from the <hi>Pontify</hi> to do any thing that might take away the Kings suspicion of him, and the <hi>Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> party, looked upon those So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Protestations and dreadful Imprecations to have sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purged him from all suspici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of guilt, and therefore he thought himself obliged in point of Justice to pronounce him innocent, wherefore rising from his Seat he lifted him up from his knees, imbracing him with the greatest passion and Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness imaginable; assuring him that he would not for the future entertain any suspicious thoughts of him again, and that for the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:39213:58"/>time to come he would look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on those as his Enemies, and to have a design against his Life, that should charge him with Treason, or so much as favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Traitors.</p>
            <p>After this they dined and spent the whole afternoon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: the Prince finding the King in so good an humour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to improve it, not only for the further ingratiating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self into the Kings Favour, but also to settle in the Kings mind an ill opinion and an Irremova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Jealousy of the <hi>Calvenians,</hi> and all that adhere to them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading him they were the only People he had any occasion to fear, and that all their fear and Accusations of, and Clamorous noise against the <hi>Gregorians,</hi> was designed for nothing else but to prevent the Kings observing and preventing the Rebellion
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:39213:58"/>which they were certainly form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against him, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behooved the King to look about him in time, and take down and suppress their tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hopes, before it be too late, least if it should be neglected, it prove as fatal to him as to his Father.</p>
            <p>The Prince could hardly sleep that night for joy to think what success he had in his dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not doubting but in a little time he should accomplish his ambitious and bloody designs, and mount himself to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Top and Pinnacle of honour. The next morning he sent for all the Confederates and declared to them what success he had ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterday with the King, the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof was so pleasant and delightful, that it toxicated their fancies, and made them drunk with joy, the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grooms
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39213:59"/>marriage, nor the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives Liberty, are not attended with half so much Pleasure and Content, Mirth and Rejoicing, as then abounded among these bloody minded <hi>Gregorians;</hi> who imagining they had now sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted all difficulties, and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd every thing that might stand in their way, hugged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in their imaginary Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, and fancying they were already dividing the spoil, it was resolved on, that the Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Estates of such of the <hi>Luteranian</hi> Nobles should be so and so disposed of. But at last one somewhat wiser than the rest advised them, <hi>To find out some way to get rid of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, before they disposed of their Estates, especially the Prince of</hi> Glascedo, <hi>who has such a subtil Head that whilst it stands upon his Shoulders, I can never</hi> (said
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:39213:59"/>he) <hi>think we are safe, for he hath wit and pollicy enough to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all our designs, and for ought I know, he may at last procure our ruine if we do not speedily procure his;</hi> the whole company was of his mind, and presently entred into a resolution to have him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, what ever it should cost them; then they debated what methods they should take in effecting it, and after the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and debating several ways, they at last resolved on this as the most feizable, that the Prince should make it his business to insinuate to the King, that by a strange accident he understood the Prince of <hi>Glascedo</hi> had some great designes on foot which he feared was to the Kings prejudice, and if the King seemed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about it, and appeared desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to know more of it, he was then to promise his utmost in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39213:60"/>to discover the whole intreague, and after some little time he must come in great hast to the King, and pretend to have discovered the depth of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign by drawing over one that was actually imployed by him, in the management thereof, and that it was no less then the rais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an army and levelling war against the King, intending to feiz his person when he went to <hi>Oclano,</hi> and whilst the Prince managed this part with the King, they promised to imploy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in procuring some despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Villains that should for a good reward swear against him, whatsoever they should dictate, and affirm that they themselves were secretly listed in this Army; but above all other things they concluded it most necessary to bring over to their side some of the late witnesses of the <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:39213:60"/>Conspiracy; which they thought was not now so diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult as formerly, since they had so well prepared the way by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing them to be deprived of their Pensions, and thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poverished, and therefore its more then probable that golden Offers and promises of future preferment would not be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at that time of the day, nor were they deceived therein; for they found them ready enough to comply, nor is it to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, that men whose first motive to discover the <hi>Gregorian</hi> Conspiracy, was not any aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation they had to their Treason, nor was it any hatred they had to the <hi>Gregorian</hi> Party, or love to the <hi>Luteranian</hi> Religion, but fear of being discovered and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused by others, to prevent which, and save their necks, they came in; but now finding the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:39213:61"/>Plot discredited, themselves dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced, and a way open whereby they might return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the <hi>Gregorian</hi> Interest, which they now saw was most favour'd, and was like to be the prevailing side, wherewith they were well enough pleased, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never heartily imbraced the <hi>Luteranians</hi> cause; and not only so, but they should be received by the <hi>Gregorians</hi> upon more advantagious terms then ever they were before) should wheel about and return to their first station, herein imitating the Mariner, who fearing a storm Shelters himself in the Harbor; but the Storm being over, he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to Sea again.</p>
            <p>Thus all things went on briskly, and they were more flushed with hopes then ever: the King being preposessed with a jealous opinion of the Prince
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:39213:61"/>of <hi>Glascedo,</hi> was the more easily inclined to believe his Brothers information, and to confirm it the more, some of their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence were brought to him, who were so confident in their assertion, and related every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular with so much formality, that the King though the never heard any thing made out clearer than this, wherefore he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently commanded him to appear before him; the poor Gentleman not imagining there were such Snares laid for him, went imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to know the Kings pleasure, who commanded he should be conveyed to <hi>Stratinco Castle,</hi> and there kept in safe Custody; this was such a step, as they thought, towards the effecting their design, that I want words wherewith to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press their Joy: <hi>Pompey</hi> or <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar</hi> were not so proud of the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:39213:62"/>Triumphs as the <hi>Gregorians</hi> were of this victory; great preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were made for his Tryal, and they fancied themselves rid of him already: but unfortunate fools, by a too fierce and eager hunting down their Prey, they spoiled all and nipt their budding hopes in the Spring, for whereas usually such base and barbarous designs are spoiled by a too slow or timorous Proceeding therein, this on the contrary was dashed and came to nothing, by reason that their Rage and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice made them drive on with so much impetuosity and fierceness that they over-did it. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had Witness e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have condemned half the men in <hi>Otenia,</hi> yet to make sure work, they were still gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of more, whereby they did the accused Prince more kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness then he was at that time
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:39213:62"/>capable of doing himself; and effected more towards the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing of his Innocency, then could otherwise have been done by himself and all the Friends he had; for by tampering with so many, they did at last meet with some who were too honest to be drawn into such sanguine designs, and too wise to be baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled or terrified from revealing what endeavours were used to perswade them thereunto, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they smoothered this up as well as they could, and resolved to strike home, and make amends for all at his Trial, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but they should get him condemned; but there they fell into the same error of overdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, for the Witnesses ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused him of many very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable and almost impossible things which his Judges could not believe him Guilty of, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:39213:63"/>he was acquitted, to the great Joy of the <hi>Luteranian</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to the grief and confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Gregorian</hi> Faction: this made them lay about them like enraged Lions, not only because their Prey, the innocent Prince, had escaped, but because by this means a great number of the Princes and Noble Men of <hi>Ote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> whose Lives and Estates they intended should have followed the Fate of the Prince of <hi>Glasce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> had escaped those Snares which were laid for them: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this was not all the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief which came by this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces escape, for now abundance of the <hi>Luteranians</hi> who by length of time and the subtil insinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of such of the <hi>Gregorians</hi> as had for that purpose disguised themselves in the habit of the <hi>Luteranians,</hi> had entertained doubtful opinions concerning
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:39213:63"/>the reality of the <hi>Gregorian</hi> conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and were strangely wheed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into a firm belief that there was certainly a <hi>Calvenian</hi> Plot, begun to be inlightned, and to perceive that the first was true, although neglected and stifled, and the other fictitious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived by the <hi>Gregorians</hi> to stifle the noise and obliterate the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their own.</p>
            <p>However the <hi>Gregorians,</hi> though they fail'd of their expectations, yet they got a considerable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, for although they got not the life of their enemies, yet they sav'd the life of their Friends, by making the Witnesses against them invalidate their own Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; notwithstanding which, they were in continual fear least the King should at last get some insight into their mischievous doings, and penetrate into their works of darkness; to prevent
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39213:64"/>which great care was taken to keep the King always im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, either in talking, or hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Fishing, or else in visit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or frequenting of Masks and Balls, or the like Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby they did their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most endeavour to prevent his having any time to consider or contemplate the present po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture of affairs, and if they found him at any time Solitary or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, they would presently divert him either by discoursing of the Court-Ladies, to whom he was no Enemy, praysing the Beauty of some and highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the Wit of others, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling the free Jovial and affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Temper, and Carriage of the Ladies of the present Age above the Coyness and Reservedness of the Ladies of the last Age; at other times, they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat their former discourse of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:39213:64"/>the great Loyalty of the Prince of <hi>Purdino,</hi> and the great ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which he had formerly done for the King, greatly commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the excellence of his Temper, in bearing his present troubles with such a Princely Fortitude, admiring much how he could so patiently bear the daily Affronts of his insolent Adversaries, insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating that hereby it plainly appeared the Prince had so much Respect and Zeal for the Kings Peace and Quiet, that he chose rather to relinquish and forego his right then be any occasion of difference or jealousie between his Highness and the people of <hi>Otenia,</hi> bitterly exclaiming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the proud ambitious and aspiring mind of the young Prince of <hi>Burranto,</hi> blaming his rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and undutiful Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards such an indulgent Father, highly agravating the pretended
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:39213:65"/>unnatural and Disloyal Obstina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he discovered by continuing his intimacy and Familiarity with the Prince of <hi>Glascedo,</hi> mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously transforming every ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Fault into an unpardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Crime, by which means they procured the King to Confide in a false and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Brother, and to entertain fears and jealousies of one of the most Loyal and Dutiful Sons that ever Prince was bless'd withal. By these and the like means they kept the King from penetrating into their designs, and preserved themselves in his favour and Friendship.</p>
            <p>Their next design was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the people from getting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Knowledge of their design, to which end they had recourse to methods which had been ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable and advantagious to them upon former occasions, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:39213:65"/>sending some of their creatures to all houses and places of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Meetings, to insinuate and affirm that some of the Judges of the Prince of <hi>Glascedo</hi> were as Guilty as himself, and that they being the Majority sway'd, and over-ruled the rest, so that they acquitted him for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son but for fear least if they should have done otherwise they should thereby have made way to themselves; they likewise caused innumerable Papers to be every where scattered about, to the like purpose, by these and the like Juggles did the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorians</hi> keep unthinking people from inquiring into and detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their cursed and Hellish Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations.</p>
            <p>Now since the Prince of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dino</hi> is so frequently mentioned in this History, it will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss to describe him. <hi>Helclesius</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:39213:66"/>Prince of <hi>Purdino</hi> was tall, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what Slender, but exactly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned; he had Black bright Eyes, Fair long curled Hair, a fresh Ruddy Complection, a Fierce and Austeer Look, a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Couragious and Undaunted Mind, a good Wit, a quick Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension, and a deep Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; he was Liberal in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and severe in his Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he was constant in his Love and Implacable in his Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, never Forgetting or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving the least Injury; which rendred him the hope of his Friends, and the Dread and Terror of his Enemies.</p>
            <p>It so sell out that the King, the Prince of <hi>Purdino,</hi> and other Noble-men being one day a hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wild Beasts in the desert, they killed abundance of Lyons, Bears, Wolves, Tigers, Bores, and other sorts of Creatures that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:39213:66"/>inhabit in that vast and Solitary Wilderness; and the King being abundantly satisfied and extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well pleased with the sport and Recreations, the variety of Creatures had yeilded him, he thought it time to return; whereupon he gave notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to his Company, and as they were riding home-ward, merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discoursing of the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the day, their discourse was suddenly interrupted by the appearance of a fierce overgrown Leopard, upon sight whereof the Prince intreated leave of the King to let loose the Dogs upon him, assuring the King that he was resolved, if his Highness would consent to it, not to leave the Chace, untill he had slain him. Pray Brother be content, <hi>replyed the King,</hi> and satisfie your self with what you have done already, I think we have done
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:39213:67"/>enough for one day; Besides, <hi>said he,</hi> our Dogs are quite tired and out of Heart. I have, <hi>replyed the Prince,</hi> three or four brace of stout Mongrels that have not been played yet, the King being prevailed upon by his Brother, consented, though at that time it was contrary to his Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereupon the Dogs were let loose, and the game pursued so hard by the Prince and the rest of the Nobles, that the King who was somewhat weary and withal not so eager of the Game as the rest, lost sight of them and was left alone in the Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erness, whereupon he set Spurs to his Horse in hope to find and overtake the Hunters, but all to no purpose, for he wandered up and down all the rest of the day and part of the night with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being able to discover his Company or find his way out of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:39213:67"/>the Wilderness, great was the fears and perplexities, of this distressed Prince, especially when Night came, when instead of resting his weary Limbs upon a Bed of Down or an imbroider'd couch, he was necessitated either to sit his horse, who began now to be as weary and tired as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, or else to alight and lye down upon the ground, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it agreed well enough with the Knights of old, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ured themselves to such kind of hardships by Custom and Practise, yet it must certainly be unpleasant as well as danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to a Prince who had not lain out of a Bed for many years together; and chuse which he would of these, he was sure to have no other canopy but that of Heaven, nor other musick than the Roaring of Lyons and howling of Wolves, or screech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:39213:68"/>of Owles, nor other Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, then the wild Beasts of the Desert which were more like to prey upon and devour him, then to guard and secure him from those that would do so; and that which still agravated and heightned his Misery was, the finding himself grow faint, and almost parch'd up with Thirst; and such was the deplorableness of his Condition, that he knew not what to do, or what Course to take: but on a sudden he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily espied a very pleasing and welcome Sight which revived his Spirits, and as it were inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him with new Life, for as he was looking about, he saw a Light at some distance, which resolving to follow, it led him to a lone Country-House where being arrived he knocked at the door, and desired to speak with the Master of the House, who
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:39213:68"/>presently came, and demanding what accident might occasion his being upon the Road so late, desired to know his pleasure with him: Sir, <hi>replyed the King,</hi> I was this day a Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Company with the King and his Nobles, and unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately losing Company with them, was not afterwards able either to find them or my way out of the Desert, wherein I have ever since wandered, and had done so all night, if it had not been my hap to espie a light in your House, which led me hither, wherefore I intreat you to entertain me in your House to night, and I will give you what satisfaction you will desire. The Countryman looking upon him, and seeing him to be a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teel Person, and well mounted, replyed with a very good will, Sir, pray alight and come in for
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:39213:69"/>you shall be as welcome to my house, and what poor entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it will afford, and that without any other satisfaction than your kind acceptation, as you can be at your own; the King wanted not intreating, and therefore without any more Complements he went in, where he was kindly received and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed by the Mistress of the House; who presently ordered the getting ready something for his Supper, of which the King eat very heartily, and thought it the Best and Sweetest Meat that ever he eat in his Life; and after Supper being somewhat refreshed, and finding the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Man and his Wife of a good brisk Jovial Temper, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving withal that they pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed larger Soules, and were Owners of better understandings then he had usually found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:39213:69"/>such Country Rusticks, resolved to divert himself by discoursing a little before he went to Bed, and to introduce the discourse, he told them the adventures of the day, describing in a particular manner every Action, and Painted out the Pleasure of their Recreation with so much Rhetorick that the poor Country Man and his Wife with all their Plow-men and Dary Maids got round about him, and Listened with such Eagerness and Atention as though they would have eaten his words; nor indeed can I blame them, for he was Master of so much Eloquence, that to hear him relate the manner of any Action afforded abundantly more Pleasure then to have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at the Action it self; great was the Admiration which this discourse begot in these Country
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:39213:70"/>People of their Royal Guest, who not being accustomed to such Visiters, thought themselves the happiest People living, that he happened to their House; but if they pleased themselves so much with entertaining an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Gentleman, how proud would they have been had they known him to be their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign. After this the King asked them what News they had in the Countrey? Why truely, <hi>replied the Countrey man,</hi> you must not expect to hear News among us, for we have none but what we have from <hi>Carmanio,</hi> and therefore I would intreat you to impart some to us, since you came so lately thence. I know but little, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the King;</hi> all the talk now is about the <hi>Calvenian</hi> Plot, what do you in the Countrey think of that? Truely, <hi>replied the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman,</hi>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:39213:70"/>we look upon it as a meer Contrivance of the <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> to acquit themselves of the Odium and Guilt of their own Plot; and to tell you the truth, we look upon the Prince of <hi>Burranto</hi> to be the true Heir of the Crown, and not the Prince of <hi>Purdino;</hi> we know not upon what pretended reasons of State <hi>Purdino</hi>'s Creatures have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with the King to deny him, but we are informed, there are some few persons yet living, who were present both at the Kings Marriage with his Mother, and at the Birth of the Prince. The King wondered to hear such discourse from such Country People, and was extreamly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and delighted with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and pleasant Conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but finding himself some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what drowsy, he desired to go to Bed, and was presently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:39213:71"/>to his Chamber, which although it were not so Richly Furnished as those of his own Pallaces, yet he found it very neat, and what was wanting in Costliness, was made up in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santness; it being curiously deckt and Adorned with great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the most beautiful and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Flowers, wherewith he was so much delighted that he would willingly have lain awake all night to have enjoyed the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their fragrant Scent, yet he was no sooner in his Bed, but he found prevailing sleep too pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful to be resisted, for sitting heavy on his Eye-lids, and soft Slumber spreading her Downy Wings o're his Royal Limbs, dissolv'd him into Rest, where we will leave him to Injoy the Sweetest Nights Repose he had been blest with in many yeares, and return to the Wilderness
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:39213:71"/>where we find the Prince fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Leopard, till night grew on a pace, without being able to kill him; wherefore they were forced to give over the Chase, and gather the Company together to return home; when, and not before, they mist the King; whereat the Prince raged like a man Distracted, not for any love he had to his Brother, or fear of any Danger that had befallen him, for if he could have been but assured he had been killed by some wild Beast, or so lost as never to have been heard of again, he would have account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it the smallest loss, or rather the greatest gain that ever he had in his life: but that which grieved him was, the fear he was in least this Accident might unravel all his designs, and that some blunt Countrey Boar should by two or three plain words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:39213:72"/>all that in a moment, which he had with Machiavillian Craft, and Dissimulation been many years in doing, <hi>viz.</hi> Undeceive the King; wherefore he caused the Company to disperse, and some ride one way, and some an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in search of the King, if happily they might light on him, and thereby prevent his falling into discourse with any who might unhappily discover some of their Mysterious Intreagues.</p>
            <p>The King never waked all Night, but when the Morning began to aproach, and the Bright Sun, great Ruler of the Day, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by his Powerful Rayes dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the Gloomy Shades, and banished the darkness of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Night, he began to rouz himself; and having shaken off the Fetters wherewith <hi>Morpheus</hi> great Monarch of the Night had bound up his Royal Senses, he
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:39213:72"/>drew the Curtain, looking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout for his Usual Guard and Attendance; and seeing none of them, but the Room in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Silence, he could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently imagine where he was, or how he came there: but being throughly awake, and recollect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his thoughts, he soon called to Mind the several Passages of the preceding day; whereupon he arose, and being dressed took two or three turns about the Chamber, greatly admiring and pleasing himself with the Neatness thereof, which yeilded an equal satisfaction to the Senses of seeing and smelling, nor was he less pleased with its Pleasant and Healthful Situation: he had not been long stirring ere the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the house, who diligently harkened whether he could hear his Royal Guest, understood by his walking about the Room
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:39213:73"/>that he had left his Bed, and therefore atttended him, inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how he had rested? Very well, <hi>replyed the Prince,</hi> I think I never slept sounder in my life: the Country man expressed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Joy thereat, intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him that since he had been so happily directed to his house, he would do him the honour to stay and dine with him, the King desired to be excused, but yet upon his importunity he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented, and found his entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment very much to exceeed his expectation; dinner being over, and his Horse and all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got ready and having taken his leave, he mounted and Rode towards <hi>Carmanio,</hi> until he came to a pleasant Path way that led unto a delightful Shady Grove situated upon an Hill, from whence he might take a view of the neighbouring Vallies, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:39213:73"/>having viewed it he dismounted and entered the Grove, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very much delighted with the umbrage, sat himself down beneath the spreading Boughs, on the flowery Bank of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stal Spring, whose Murmuring Streams in Silver Trills dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themselves into a neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Brook, and with much admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration took a delightful view of the out spread Plaines and Vallies, which were Curiously fringed with Trees and Blossom'd Shrubs, nor was he less delighted to see the careful Shepherds Feeding their Numerous Flocks, whose pritty Bleatings answered still those rural Songs which they on Slender Reeds Tuned, Harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the Musick of the Spheres; nor was there any other Rustick Exercise or Pleasing Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject wanting to his Sight, which had hitherto been repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:39213:74"/>to his View in Land-skips dextrously drawn by the most curious Pencils, where we at present leave him to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 9. <hi>line</hi> 14. <hi>Read</hi> Carriage, p. 24. L. 24. R. to, p. 27 L. 9. <hi>after</hi> to, <hi>add</hi> aid, p. 75. L. 12. R. Extremity, L. 23. R. Reitterated, p. 82. L. 7. R. and then.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39213:74"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>